so today we are gonna be covering quite
a lot of materials so I will try not to
run but then yesterday young scooped me
completely so young talked about exactly
the same things I wanted to talk today
so I'm gonna go a bit faster please slow
me down if you actually are somehow lost
okay
so I will just try to be a little bit
faster than you sir
so today we are gonna be talking about
recurrent neural networks record neural
networks are one type of architecture we
can use in order to be to deal with
sequences of data what are sequences
what type of signal is a sequence
temporal is a temporal component but we
already seen data with temporal
component how what are they called
what dimensional what is the dimension
of that kind of signal so on the
convolutional net lesson we have seen
that a signal could be one this signal
to this signal 3d signal based on the
domain and the domain is what you map
from to go to right so temporal handling
sequential sequences of data is
basically dealing with one the data
because the domain is going to be just
the temporal axis nevertheless you can
also use RNN to deal with you know two
dimensional data you have double
Direction okay okay so this is a
classical neural network in the diagram
that is I'm used to draw where I
represent each in this case bunch of
neurons like each of those is a vector
and for example the X is my input vector
it's in pink as usual then I have my
hidden layer in a green in the center
then I have my final blue eared lane
layer which is the output network so
this is a three layer neural network in
my for my notation and so if some of you
are familiar with digital electronics
this is like talking about a
combinatorial logic your current output
depends only on the current input and
that's it there is no
there is no other input instead when we
are talking about our men we are gonna
be talking about something that looks
like this in this case our output here
on the right hand side depends on the
current input and on the state of the
system and again if you're a king of
digital electronics this is simply
sequential logic whereas you have an
internal state the onion is the
dimension flip-flop if you have no idea
what a flip-flop you know check it out
it's just some very basic memory unit in
digital electronics nevertheless this is
the only difference right in the first
case you have an output which is just
function of the input in the second case
you have an output which is function of
the input and the state of the system
okay that's the big difference yeah
vanilla is in American term for saying
it's plane doesn't have a taste that
American sorry I try to be the most
American I can in Italy you feel taken
an ice cream which is doesn't have a
taste it's gonna be fury laughter which
is milk taste in here we don't have milk
tests they have vanilla taste which is
the plain ice cream
okay Americans sorry
all right so oh so let's see what does
it change this with young representation
so young draws those kind of little
funky things here which represent a
mapping between a TENS tensor to another
painter from one a vector to another
vector right so there you have your
input vector X is gonna be mapped
through this item here to this hidden
representation so that actually
represent my fine transformation so my
rotation Plus this question then you
have the heater representation that you
have another rotation is question then
you get the final output right similarly
in the recurrent diagram you can have
these additional things this is a fine
transformation squashing that's like a
delay module with a final transformation
excursion and now you have the final one
affine transformation and squashing
right these things is making noise okay
sorry all right so what is the first
case first case is this one is a vector
to sequence so we input one bubble the
pink wonder and then you're gonna have
this evolution of the internal state of
the system the green one and then as the
state of the system evolves you can be
spitting out at every time stamp one
specific output what can be an example
of this kind of architecture so this one
could be the following my input is gonna
be one of these images and then the
output is going to be a sequence of
characters representing the English
description of whatever this input is so
for example in the center when we have a
herd of elephants so the last one herd
of elephants walking across a dry grass
field so it's very very very well
refined right then you have in the
center here for example two dogs play in
the in the grass maybe there are three
but okay they play they're playing in
the grass right so it's cool in this
case you know a red motorcycle park on
the side of the road
looks more pink or you know a little
blow a little a little girl in the pink
that is blowing bubbles that she's not
blowing right anything there all right
and then you also have you know even
more wrong examples right so you have
like yellow school bus parked in the
parking lot
well it's CL um but it's not a school
bus so it can be failing as well but I
also can do a very very nice you know
you can also perform very well so this
was from one input vector which is B for
example representation of my image to a
sequence of symbols which are D for
example characters or words that are
making here my English sentence okay
clear so far yeah okay another kind of
usage you can have is maybe the
following so you're gonna have sequence
two final vector okay so I don't care
about the intermediate sequences so okay
the top right is called Auto regressive
network and outer regressive network is
a network which is outputting an output
given that you feel as input the
previous output okay
so this is called Auto regressive you
have this kind of loopy part on the
network on the left hand side instead
I'm gonna be providing several sequences
yeah
that's gonna be the English translation
so you have a sequence of words that are
going to make up your final sentence
it's it's blue there you can think about
a index in a dictionary and then each
blue is going to tell you which word
you're gonna pick on an indexed
dictionary right so this is a school bus
right so oh yeah a yellow school bus you
go to a index of a then you have second
index you can figure out that is yellow
and then school box right so the
sequence here is going to be
representing the sequence of words the
model is out on the other side there on
the left you're gonna have instead I
keep feeding a sequence of symbols and
only at the end I'm gonna look what is
my final output what can be an
application of this one so something yun
also mentioned was different so let's
see if I can get my network to compile
Python or to an open pilot own
interpretation so in this case I have my
current input which I feed my network
which is going to be J equal 8580 for
then for X in range eight some - J 920
blah blah blah and then print this one
and then my network is going to be
tasked with the just you know giving me
twenty five thousand and eleven okay so
this is the final output of a program
and I enforced in the network to be able
to output me the correct output the
correct in your solution of this program
or even more complicated things for
example I can provide a sequence of
other symbols which are going to be
eighty eight thousand eight hundred
thirty seven then I have C is going to
be something then I have print this one
if something that is always true as the
other one and then you know the output
should be twelve thousand eight 184
right so you can train a neural net to
do these operations so you feed a
sequence of symbols and then at the
output you just enforce that the final
target should be a specific value okay
and these things making noise okay maybe
I'm better
all right so what's next next is going
to be for example a sequence to vector
to sequence this used to be the standard
way of performing length language
translation so you start with a sequence
of symbols here shown in pink so you
have a sequence of inputs then
everything gets condensed into this kind
of final age which is this H over here
which is going to be somehow my concept
right so I have a sentence I squeeze the
sentence temporal information into just
one vector which is representing the
meaning the message I'd like to send
across and then I get this meaning in
whatever representation unrolled back in
a different language right so I can
encode I don't know today I'm very happy
in English as a sequence of word and
then you know you can get LG Sonoma to
Felicia and then I speak outside
Thailand today or whatever now today I'm
very tired
Jin Chen walk han lei or whatever ok so
again you have some kind of encoding
then you have a compressed
representation and then you get like the
decoding given the same compressed
version ok and so for example I guess
language translation again recently we
have seen transformers and a lot of
things like in the recent time so we're
going to cover that the next lesson I
think but this used to be the state of
the art until few two years ago and here
you can see that if you actually check
if you do a PCA over the latent space
you have that words are grouped by
semantics ok so if we zoom in that
region there are we're gonna see that in
what in the same location you find all
the amounts december february november
whatever right if you put a few focus on
a different region you get that a few
days
next few miles and so on right so
different location will have some
specific you know common meaning so we
basically see in this case how by
training these networks you know just
with symbols they will pick up on some
specific semantics
you know features right in this case you
can see like there is a vector so the
vector that is connecting women to men
is gonna be the same vector that is well
woman - man which is this one I think is
gonna be equal to Queen - King right and
so yeah it's correct and so you're gonna
have that the same distance in this
embedding space will be applied to
things that are female and male for
example or in the other case you have
walk-in and walked swimming and swamp so
you always have this you know specific
linear transformation you can apply in
order to go from one type of word to the
other one or this one you have the
connection between cities and the
capitals all right so one more right I
think what's missing from the big
picture here it's a big picture because
it's so large no no it's such a big
picture because it's the overview okay
you didn't get the joke it's okay what's
missing here vector to seek with no okay
good but no because you can still use
the other one so you have this one the
vector is sequence to sequence right so
this one is you start feeding inside
inputs you start outputting something
right what can be an example of this
stuff so if you had a Nokia phone and
you use the t9 you know this stuff from
20 years ago you have basically
suggestions on what your typing is
you're typing right so this would be one
type of these suggestions where like one
type of this architecture as you getting
suggestions as you're typing things
through or you may have like speech to
captions right I talked and you have the
things
below or something very cool which is
the following so I start writing here
the rings of Saturn glitter while the
harsh ice two men look at each other hmm
okay they were enemies but the server
robots weren't okay okay hold on
so this network was trained on some
sci-fi novels and therefore you can just
type something then you let the network
start outputting some suggestions for
you so you know if you don't know how to
write a book then you can you know ask
your computer to help you out okay
that's so cool or one more that I really
like it this one is fantastic I think
you should read read it I think so you
put some kind of input there like the
scientist named alone what is it
or the prompt right so you put in the
the top prompt and then you get you know
this network start writing about very
interesting unicorns with multiple horns
is called horns say unicorn right okay
alright let's so cool just check it out
later and you can take a screenshot of
the screen anyhow so that was like the
eye candy such that you get you know
hungry now let's go into be PTT which is
the thing that they aren't really like
yesterday's PTT said okay alright let's
see how this stuff works okay so on the
left hand side we see again this vector
middle in the representation the output
to a fine transformation and then there
we have the classical equations right
all right so let's see how this stuff is
similar or not similar and you can't see
anything so for the next two seconds I
will want one minute I will turn off the
lights then I turn them on
[Music]
okay now you can see something all right
so let's see what are the questions of
this new architecture don't stand up
you're gonna be crushing yourself
alright so you have here the hidden
representation now there's gonna be this
nonlinear function of this rotation of a
stack version of my input which I
appended the previous configuration of
the hidden layer okay and so this is a
very nice compact notation it's just I
just put the two vectors one on top of
each other and then I sign assign I sum
the bias I also and define initial
condition my initial H is gonna be 0 so
at the beginning whenever I have T equal
1 this stuff is gonna be settle is a
vector of zeros and then I have this
matrix WH is gonna be two separate
matrices so sometimes you see this a
question is wh x times x plus w HH times
h t minus 1 but you can also figure out
that if you stock those two matrices you
know one attached to the other that you
just put this two vertical lines
completely equivalent notation but it
looked like very similar to whatever we
had here so hidden layer is affine
transformation of the input inner layer
is affine transformation of the input
and the previous value okay and then you
have the final output is going to be
again my final rotation so I'm gonna
turn on the light so no magic so far
right you're okay right you're with me
to shake the heads what about the others
no yes okay whatever
so this one is simply on the right hand
side I simply unroll over time such that
you can see how things are just not very
crazy like this loop here is not
actually a loop this is like a
connection to
next time steps right so that around
arrow means is just this right arrow so
this is a neural net it's dinkley a
neural net which is extended in in
length rather also not only in a in a
thickness right so you have a network
that is going this direction input and
output but as you can think as there's
been an extended input and this been an
extended output while all these
intermediate weights are all share right
so all of these weights are the same
weights and then you use this kind of
shared weights so it's similar to a
convolutional net in the sense that you
had this parameter sharing right across
different time domains because you
assume there is some kind of you know
stationarity right of the signal make
sense so this is a kind of convolution
right you can see how this is kind of a
convolution alright so that was kind of
you know a little bit of the theory we
already seen that so let's see how this
works for a practical example so in this
case we we are just reading this code
here so this is world language model you
can find it at the PI torch examples so
you have a sequence of symbols I have
just represented there every symbol is
like a letter in the alphabet and then
the first part is gonna be basically
splitting this one in this way right
so you preserve vertically in the time
domain but then I split the long long
long sequence such that I can now chop I
can use best bets bets how do you say
computation so the first thing you have
the best size is gonna be 4 in this case
and then I'm gonna be getting in my
first batch and then I will force the
network to be able to so this will be my
best back propagation through time
period and I will force the network to
output the next sequence of characters
ok so given that I have ABC I will force
my network to say D given that I have
GHI I will force the network to
come up with J givin em an orbit for
tonight poke at P and s tu for the
network 20 right so how can you actually
make sure you understand what I'm saying
whenever you are able to predict my next
world you're actually able to you know
you basically know in already what I'm
saying right yeah so by trying to
predict an upcoming word you're going to
be showing some kind of comprehension of
whatever is going to be this temporal
information in the data all right so
after we get the beds we have so how
does it work let's actually see you know
and about a bit of a detail this is
gonna be my first output is going to be
a batch with four items I feed this
inside the near corner all night and
then my neural net we come up with a
prediction of the upcoming sample right
and I will force that one to be my B H
and T okay then I'm gonna be having my
second input I will provide the previous
hidden state to the current RNN I will
feel these inside and then I expect to
get the second line of the output the
target right and then so on right I get
the next state and sorry the next input
I get the next state and then I'm gonna
get inside the neural net the RN n I
which I will try to force to get the
final target okay so far yeah
each one is gonna be the output of the
internet recurrent neural net right I'll
show you the equation before you have h1
comes out from this one right second the
output I'm gonna be forcing the output
actually to be my target my next word in
the sequence of letters right so I have
a sequence of words force my network to
predict what's the next word given the
previous word know h1 is going to be fed
inside here and you stuck the next word
the next word together with the previous
state and then you'll do a rotation of
the previous word with a previous sorry
the new word with the next state the new
word with the previous state you'll do
our rotation here find transformation
right and then you apply the
non-linearity so you always get a new
word that is the current X and then you
get the previous state just to see in
what state the system once and then you
output a new output right and so we are
in this situation here we have a bunch
of inputs I have my first input and then
I get the first output I have this
internal memory that is sent forward and
then this network will now be aware of
what happened here and then I input the
next input and so on I get the next
output and I force the output to be the
output here the value inside the batch
ok alright what's missing now
[Music]
this is for PowerPoint drawing
constraint all right what's happening
now so here I'm gonna be sending the
here I just drawn an arrow with the
final HT but there is a slash on the
arrow
what is the slash on the arrow who can
understand what the slash mean of course
there will be there is gonna be the next
batch they're gonna be starting from
here D and so on this is gonna be my
next batch d j pv e KQ v + FL rx right
so this slash here means do not back
propagate through okay so that one is
gonna be calling dot detach in Porsche
which is gonna be stopping the gradient
to be you know propagated back to
forever okay so this one say know that
and so whenever I get the sorry no no
gradient such that when I input the next
gradient the first input here it's gonna
be this guy over here and also of course
without gradient such that we don't have
an infinite length RN n okay make sense
yes
no I assume it's a yes
okay so vanishing and exploding
gradients we touch them upon these also
yesterday so again I'm kind of going a
little bit faster to the intent user so
let's see how this works
so usually for our recurrent neural
network you have an input you have a
hidden layer and then you have an output
then this value of here how do you get
this information through here what what
what does this R represent do you
remember the equation of the hidden
layer so the new hidden layer is gonna
be the previous hidden layer which we
rotate
alright so we rotate the previous hidden
layer and so how do you rotate hidden
layers matrices right and so every time
you see all ads on tile arrow there is a
rotation there is a matrix
now if the you know this matrix can
change the sizing of your final output
right so if you think about perhaps
let's say the determinant right if the
terminal is unitary it's a mapping the
same areas for the same area if it's
larger than one they're going to be
getting you know this radians to getting
larger and larger or if it's smaller
than I'm gonna get these gradients to go
to zero whenever you perform the back
propagation in this direction okay so
the problem here is that whenever we do
is send gradients back so the gains are
going to be going down like that are
gonna be going like down like this then
down like this way and down like this
way and also all down this way and so on
right so the gradients are going to be
always going against the direction of
the arrow in H ro has a matrix inside
right and again this matrix will affect
how these gradients propagate and that's
why you can see here although we have a
very bright input that one like gets
lost through oh well if you have like a
gradient coming down here the gradient
gets you know kill over time okay so how
do we fix that to fix this one we simply
remove the matrices in this horizontal
operation does it make sense no yes no
the problem is that the next hidden
state will have you know its own input
memory coming from the previous step
through a matrix multiplication now this
matrix multiplication will affect what's
gonna be the gradient that comes in the
other direction okay
so whenever you have an output here you
have a final loss now you have the grade
that are gonna be going against the
arrows up to the input the problem is
that this gradient which is going
through the in the opposite direction of
these arrows will be multiplied by the
matrix right the transpose of the matrix
and again these matrices will affect
what is the overall norm of this
gradient right and it will be all
killing it
you have vanishing gradient or you're
gonna have exploding the gradient which
is going to be whenever is going to be
getting amplified right so in order to
be avoiding that we have to avoid so you
can see this is a very deep network so
recurrently our network where the first
deep networks back in the night is
actually and the word
depth was actually in time which and of
course they were facing the same issues
we face with deep learning in modern day
days where ever we were still like
stacking several layers we were
observing that the gradients get lost as
depth right so how do we solve gradient
getting lost through the depth in a
current days
skipping constant connection right the
receiver connections we use and
similarly here we can use skip
connections as well when we go down well
up in in time okay so let's see how this
works
yeah so the problem is that the
gradients are only going in the backward
paths right back
[Music]
well the gradient has to go the same way
it went forward by the opposite
direction right I mean you're computing
chain rule so if you have a function of
a function of a function then you just
use those functions to go back right the
point is that whenever you have these
gradients coming back they will not have
to go through matrices therefore also
the forward part has not doesn't have to
go through the matrices meaning that the
memory cannot go through matrix
multiplication if you don't want to have
this effect when you perform back
propagation okay
yeah it's gonna be worth much better
working I show you in the next slide
[Music]
show you next slide
so how do we fix this problem well
instead of using one recurrent neural
network we're gonna using for recurrent
neural network okay so the first
recurrent Network alcohol on the first
network is gonna be the one that goes
from the input to this intermediate
state then I have other three networks
and each of those are represented by
these three symbols 1 2 & 3
okay think about this as our open mouth
and it's like a closed mouth okay like
the emoji okay so if you use this kind
of for net for recurrent neural network
be regular Network you gotta have for
example from the input I send things
through in the open mouth therefore it
gets here I have a closed mouth here so
nothing goes forward then I'm gonna have
this open mouth here such that the
history goes forward so the history gets
sent forward without going through a
neural network matrix multiplication
it just gets through our open mouth and
all the other inputs find a closed mouth
so the hidden state will not change upon
new inputs okay and then here you're
gonna have a open mouth here such that
you can get the final output here then
the open mouth keeps going here such
that you have another output there and
then finally you get the last closed
mouth at the last one now if you perform
back prop you will have the gradients
flowing through the open mouth and you
don't get any kind of matrix
multiplication so now let's figure out
how these open mouths are represented
how are they instantiated in like in in
terms of mathematics is it clear design
right so now we are using open and
closed mouths and each of those mouths
is plus the the first guy here that
connects the input to the hidden are
brn ends so these on here that is a
gated recurrent network it's simply for
normal recurrent neural network combined
in a clever way such that you have
multiplicative interaction and not
matrix interaction is it clear so far
this is like intuition I haven't shown
you how all right so let's figure out
who made this and how it works okay so
we're gonna see now those long short
term memory or gated recurrent neural
networks so I'm sorry okay that was the
dude okay this is the guy who actually
invented this stuff actually him and his
students back some in 1997 and we were
drinking here together okay all right so
that is the question of a recurrent
neural network and on the top left are
you gonna see in the diagram so I just
make a very compact version of this
recurrent neural network here is going
to be the collection of equations that
are expressed in a long short term
memory they look a little bit dense so I
just draw it for you here okay let's
actually goes through how this stuff
works
so I'm gonna be drawing an interactive
animation here so you have your input
gate here which is going to be an affine
transformation so all of these are
recurrent Network write the same
equation I show you here so this input
transformation will be multiplying my C
tilde which is my candidate gate here I
have a don't forget gate which is
multiplying my previous value of my cell
memory and then my Poppa stylist maybe
don't forget previous plus input ii i'm
gonna show you now how it works then i
have my final hidden representations to
be multiplication element wise
multiplication between my output gate
and my you know whatever hyperbolic
tangent version of the cell such that
things are bounded and then I have
finally my C tilde which is my candidate
gate is simply
Anette right so you have one recurrent
network one that modulates the output
one that modulates this is don't forget
gate and this is the input gate
so all this interaction between the
memory and the gates is a multiplicative
interaction and this forget input and
don't forget the input and output are
all sigmoids and therefore they are
going from 0 to 1 so I can multiply by a
0 you have a closed mouth or you can
multiply by 1 if it's open mouth right
if you think about being having our
internal linear volume which is below
minus 5 or above plus 5 okay such that
you using the you use the gate in the
saturated area or 0 or 1 right you know
the sigmoid so let's see how this stuff
works
this is the output let's turn off the
output how do I do
turn off the output I simply put a 0
inside so let's say I have a purple
internal representation see I put a 0
there in the output gate the output is
going to be multiplying a 0 with
something you get 0 okay then let's say
I have a green one I have one then I
multiply one with the purple I get
purple and then finally I get the same
value similarly I can control the memory
and I can for example we set it in this
case I'm gonna be I have my internal
memory see this is purple and then I
have here my previous guy which is gonna
be blue I guess I have a zero here and
therefore the multiplication gives me a
zero there I have here a zero so
multiplication is gonna be giving a zero
at some two zeros and I get a zero
inside of memory so I just erase the
memory and you get the zero there
otherwise I can keep the memory I still
do the internal thing I did a new one
but I keep a wonder such that the
multiplication gets blue the Sun gets
blue and then I keep sending out my
bloom finally I can write such that I
can get a 1 in the input gate the
multiplication gets purple then the I
set a zero in the don't forget such that
the
we forget and then multiplication gives
me zero I some do I get purple and then
I get the final purple output okay so
here we control how to send how to write
in memory how to reset the memory and
how to output something okay so we have
all different operation this looks like
a computer - and in an yeah it is
assumed in this case to show you like
how the logic works as we are like
having a value inside the sigmoid has
been or below minus 5 or being above
plus 5 such that we are working as a
switch 0 1 switch okay the network can
choose to use this kind of operation to
me make sense I believe this is the
rationale behind how this network has
been put together the network can decide
to do anything it wants usually they do
whatever they want but this seems like
they can work at least if they've had to
saturate the gates it looks like things
can work pretty well so in the remaining
15 minutes of kind of I'm gonna be
showing you two notebooks I kind of went
a little bit faster because again there
is much more to be seen here in the
notebooks so yeah
so this the the actual weight the actual
gradient you care here is gonna be the
gradient with respect to previous C's
right the thing you care is gonna be
basically the partial derivative of the
current seen with respect to previous
C's such that you if you have the
original initial C here and you have
multiple C over time you want to change
something in the original C you still
have the gradient coming down all the
way until the first C which comes down
to getting gradients through that matrix
WC here right so if you want to change
those weights here you just go through
the chain of multiplications that are
not involving any matrix multiplication
as such that you when you get the
gradient it still gets multiplied by one
all the time and it gets down to
whatever we want to do okay did I answer
your question
so the matrices will change the
amplitude of your gradient right so if
you have like these largest eigenvalue
being you know 0.0001 every time you
multiply you get the norm of this vector
getting killed right so you have like an
exponential decay in this case if my
forget gate is actually always equal to
1 then you get C equal C minus team
derivative what is the partial
derivative of C T with respect to what
is the partial derivative of C T with
respect to C minus t minus 1 1 right so
the parts of the relative that is the
thing that you actually multiply every
time there's gonna be 1 so output
gradient output gradients can be input
gradients right yeah i'll pavillions
gonna be implicit because it would apply
the output gradient by the derivative of
this module right if the
this module is e1 then the thing that is
here keeps going that is the rationale
behind this now this is just for drawing
purposes I assumed it's like a switch
okay such that I can make things you
know you have a switch on and off to
show like how it should be working maybe
doesn't work like that but still it
works it can work this way right yeah so
that's the implementation of pro
question is gonna be simply you just pad
all the other sync when sees with zeros
before the sequence so if you have
several several sequences yes several
sequences that are of a different length
you just put them all aligned to the
right
and then you put some zeros here okay
such that you always have in the last
column the latest element if you put two
zeros here it's gonna be a mess in right
in the code if you put the zeros in the
in the beginning you just stop doing
back propagation when you hit the last
symbol right so you start from here you
go back here so you go forward then you
go back prop and stop whenever you
actually reach the end of your sequence
if you pad on the other side you get a
bunch of drop there in the next ten
minutes so you're gonna be seen two
notebooks if you don't have other
questions okay wow you're so quiet okay
so we're gonna be going now for sequence
classification alright so in this case
I'm gonna be I just really stuff loud
out loud the goal is to classify a
sequence of elements sequence elements
and targets are represented locally
input vectors with only one nonzero bit
so it's a one hot encoding the sequence
starts with a B for beginning and end
efore end and otherwise consists of a
randomly chosen symbols from a set a b c
and d which are some kind of noise
expect for two elements in position t1
and t2 this position can be either or X
or Y in for the hard difficulty level
you have for example that the sequence
length length is chose randomly between
100 and 110 10 t1 is randomly chosen
between 10 and 20 Tinto is randomly
chosen between 50 and 60 there are four
sequences classes QRS nu which depends
on the temporal order of x and y so if
you have X X you can be getting a Q x
and y you get an R Y and X you get an S
and YY with you so we're going to be
doing a sequence classification based on
the X and y or whatever those to import
to these kind of triggers okay
and in the middle in the middle you can
have ABCD in random positions like you
know randomly generated is it clear so
far so we do cast a classification of
sequences where you may have these x and
y's or X X or Y or Y X so in this case
I'm showing you first the first input so
the return type is a tuple of sequence
of two which is going to be what is the
output of this example generator and so
let's see what is what is this thing
here so this is my data I'm going to be
feeding to the network so I have one two
three four five six seven eight there
are eight different symbols here in a
row every time why there are eight we
have x and y a b c and d beginning and
end right so we have one hot out of you
know eight characters and then i have a
sequence of rows which are my sequence
of symbols okay in this case you can see
here i have a beginning with all zeros
why is all zeros padding right so in
this case the sequence was shorter than
the expect the maximum sequence in the
bed
and then the first first sequence has an
extra zero item at the beginning in them
you're gonna have like in this case the
second item is of the two a pole to pole
is the corresponding best class for
example I have a batch size of 32 and
then I'm gonna have an output size of 4
y 4 Q R whatever right the QRS you okay
so I have 4 a 4 dimensional target
vector and I have a sequence of 8
dimensional vectors as input okay so
let's see how this sequence looks like
in this case is gonna be the beginning
BX CX CBE so X X let's see X X X X is Q
right so we have our Q sequence and
that's why the final target is a Q the 1
0 0 0 and then you're gonna see B B X C
so the second item and the second last
is gonna be B lowercase B you can see
here the second item and the second last
item is going to be a be okay all right
so let's now create a recurrent Network
in a very quick way so here I can simply
say my recurrent network is going to be
torch and an RNN and I'm gonna be using
a reader network really non-linearity
and then I have my final linear layer in
the other case I'm gonna be using a led
STM and then I'm gonna have a final
inner layer so I just execute these guys
I have my training loop and I'm gonna be
training for 10 books so in the training
group you can be always looking for
those five different steps first step is
gonna be get the data inside the model
right so that's step number one what is
step number two there are five steps we
remember hello
you feel that you feed the network if
you feed the network with some data then
what do you do you compute the loss okay
then we have compute step to compute the
loss fantastic number three is zero the
cash right then number four which is
computing the off yes lost dog backwards
lost not backward don't compute the
partial derivative of the loss with
respect to the network's parameters yeah
here backward finally number five which
is step in opposite direction of the
gradient okay all right those are the
five steps you always want to see in any
training blueprint if someone is missing
then you're [ __ ] up okay so we try now
the RNN and the lsdm and you get
something looks like this
so our NN goes up to 50% in accuracy and
then the lsdm got 100% okay oh okay
first of all how many weights does this
lsdm have compared to the RN n four
times more weights right so it's not a
fair comparison I would say because lsdm
is simply for rnns combined somehow
right so this is a two layer neural
network whereas the other one is at one
layer right always both ever like it has
one hidden layer they are an end if
Alice TM we can think about having two
hidden so again one layer two layers
well one hidden to lead in one set of
parameters four sets of the same numbers
like okay not fair okay anyway
let's go with hundred iterations okay so
now I just go with 100 iterations and I
show you how if they work or not and
also when I be just clicking things such
that we have time to go through stuff
okay now my computer's going to be
complaining all right so again what are
the five types of operations like five
okay now is already done
sorry I was going to do okay so this is
the RNN right RNN and finally actually
gave to 100% okay so iron and it just
let it more time like a little bit more
longer training actually works the other
one okay and here you can see that we
got 100% in twenty eight bucks okay the
other case we got 2,100 percent in
roughly twice as long
twice longer at a time okay so let's
first see how they perform here so I
have this sequence BC y dy Dae which is
au sequence and then we ask the network
and he actually meant for actually like
labels it as you okay so below we're
gonna be seeing something very cute so
in this case we were using sequences
that are very very very very small right
so even the RNN is able to train on
these small sequences so what is the
point of using a lsdm well we can first
of all increase the difficulty of the
training part and we're gonna see that
the RN ends can be miserably failing
whereas the lsdm keeps working in this
visualization part below okay I train a
network now Alice and lsdm now with the
moderate level which has eighty symbols
rather than eight or ten ten symbols so
you can see here how this model actually
managed to succeed at the end although
there is like a very big spike and I'm
gonna be now drawing the value of the
cell state over time okay so I'm going
to be input in our sequence of eighty
symbols and I'm gonna be showing you
what is the value of the hidden state
hidden State
so in this case I'm gonna be showing you
[Music]
hidden hold on
yeah I'm gonna be showing I'm gonna send
my input through a hyperbolic tangent
such that if you're below minus 2.5 I'm
gonna be mapping to minus 1 if you're
above 2.5 you get mapped to plus 1 more
or less and so let's see how this stuff
looks so in this case here you can see
that this specific hidden layer picked
on the X here and then it became red
until you got the other X right so this
is visualizing the internal state of the
LSD and so you can see that in specific
unit because in this case I use hidden
representation like hidden dimension of
10 and so in this case the 1 2 3 4 5 the
fifth hidden unit of the cell lay the
5th cell actually is trigger by
observing the first X and then it goes
quiet after seen the other acts this
allows me to basically you know take
care of I mean recognize if the sequence
is ru OPRS okay does it make sense okay
oh this one more notebook I'm gonna be
showing just quickly which is the Eco
data in this case I'm gonna be in South
corner I'm gonna have a network echo in
whatever I'm saying so if I say
something I asked a network to say if I
say something I asked my neighbor to say
if I say something I ask ok Anderson
right ok so in this case here and I'll
be inputting this is the first sequence
is going to be 0 1 1 1 1 0 and you'll
have the same one here 0 1 1 1 1 0 and I
have 1 0 1 1 0 1 etc right so in this
case if you want to output something
after some
right this in this case is three time
step after you have to have some kind of
short-term memory where you keep in mind
what I just said where you keep in mind
[Music]
what I just said yeah that's correct so
you know pirating actually requires
having some kind of working memory
whereas the other one the language model
which it was prompted prompted to say
something that I haven't already said
right so that was a different kind of
task you actually had to predict what is
the most likely next word in keynote you
cannot be always right right but this
one you can always be right you know
this is there is no random stuff anyhow
so I have my first batch here and then
the sec the white patch which is the
same similar thing which is shifted over
time and then we have we have to chunk
this long long long sequence so before I
was sending a whole sequence inside the
network and I was enforcing the final
target to be something right in this
case I had to chunk if the sequence goes
this direction I had to chunk my long
sequence in little chunks and then you
have to fill the first chunk keep trace
of whatever is the hidden state send a
new chunk where you feed and initially
as the initial hidden state the output
of this chant right so you feed this
chunk you have a final hidden state then
you feed this chunk and as you put you
have to put these two as input to the
internal memory right now you feed the
next chunk where you put this one as
input as to the internal state and you
we are going to be comparing here RNN
with analyst TMS I think so at the end
here you can see that okay we managed to
actually get we are an n/a accuracy that
goes 100 100 percent then if you are
starting now to mess with the size of
the memory chunk with a memory interval
you can be seen
with the lsdm you can keep this memory
for a long time as long as you have
enough capacity the RNN after you reach
some kind of length you start forgetting
what happened in the past and it was
pretty much everything for today so stay
warm wash your hands and I'll see you
next week bye bye
[Music]